<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gistify | Hi, I'm Josh Symonds]]></title>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/categories/gistify/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-22T18:49:58-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://joshsymonds.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Symonds]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gistify 1.2.0: Drag &amp; Drop Gisting]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/08/13/gistify-1-dot-2-0-drag-and-drop-gisting/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-13T10:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/08/13/gistify-1-dot-2-0-drag-and-drop-gisting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gistify just keeps getting better!</p>

<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502">Gistify 1.2.0</a> is now in the App Store, and features some awesome drag and drop magic. Drag a snippet of text or an entire file onto the Gistify icon and a new gist will be created from your file. The format of the file will automatically be detected, and the resulting gist URL added to your clipboard just as usual. Amazing!</p>

<p>In addition to that big new feature, 1.2.0 features a number of bug fixes and performance improvements: for example, now Gistify will properly start up if you check the &ldquo;Open at Startup&rdquo; box, and you can copy and paste in the GitHub username/password fields (for the 1Password or LastPass users out there). Just small quality of life improvements generally.</p>

<p>Interested in giving Gistify a shot? Go <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502">download it</a> now! Or if you&rsquo;d like to demo it without paying the $1.99, just let me know and I&rsquo;d be happy to set you up with a review copy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gistify 1.1.0: Visibility &amp; Accounts]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/06/03/gistify-1-dot-1-0-visibility-and-accounts/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T18:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/06/03/gistify-1-dot-1-0-visibility-and-accounts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hot on the heels of my <a href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/05/29/gistify-a-mac-app-for-easy-gists/">previous announcement</a>, I&rsquo;m proud to announce the release of Gistify version 1.1.0. And after submitting only four days ago &mdash; man, the Mac App store moves incredibly fast compared to the iOS App Store!</p>

<p>Anyhow, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502">Gistify</a>, the incredibly awesome Mac App that lets you gist quickly and easily, just got a whole lot better. Now you can sign in to your GitHub account to make gists, and set the visibility of your gists to either public or private Also the app screenshots are no longer quite so, well&hellip; drab, for lack of a better word.</p>

<p>If you haven&rsquo;t downloaded <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502">Gistify</a> yet, you should. While I&rsquo;m slightly biased, I&rsquo;ve been using it all the time and I think it&rsquo;s an incredibly handy tool &mdash; after all, that&rsquo;s why I released it. But if you&rsquo;re not convinced yet, or you&rsquo;re just interested in giving it a shot without paying the $2, let me know and I&rsquo;ll be happy to hook you up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gistify: a Mac App for Easy Gists]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/05/29/gistify-a-mac-app-for-easy-gists/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T13:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/05/29/gistify-a-mac-app-for-easy-gists</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&rsquo;m happy to announce the release of my very first Mac App: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502">Gistify</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502"><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/2w0L3S1A2y3H2d3S0c14/Gistify-icon-256.png" alt="Gistify" /></a></p>

<p>Gistify rather simply delivers the content of your clipboard to GitHub&rsquo;s awesome <a href="https://gist.github.com/">Gist</a> service. You can select the default format for all gists and override it on a gist-by-gist basis, and the resulting URL is appended to your clipboard so you can paste it wherever you like.</p>

<p>Simple? Yes indeed, but I desperately wanted it. I made this initial version rapidly to scratch an itch I had &mdash; and perplexingly there&rsquo;s not an existing desktop app that seems to do this already. (There are competing apps that paste to other services, but for some reason none work properly that post to Gist.)</p>

<p>In terms of future plans, I already have a new version submitted for approval to Apple! Version 1.1.0 will allow you to sign in to GitHub and create gists under your username: additionally you can toggle the visibility of gists to either public or secret. And in development is version 1.2.0, which will introduce all kinds of new mind-blowing awesomeness.</p>

<p>So what are you waiting for? Get over to the Mac App store and buy <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gistify/id653231502">Gistify</a>!</p>

<p>(Oh, and if you like the icon, it&rsquo;s by the super amazing <a href="http://twitter.com/lukesbeard">Luke Beard</a>.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
