<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: iphone | Hi, I'm Josh Symonds]]></title>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/categories/iphone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-11T14:55:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://joshsymonds.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Symonds]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iOS 7: Impressions &amp; Thoughts]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/06/11/ios-7-impressions-and-thoughts/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T12:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2013/06/11/ios-7-impressions-and-thoughts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I downloaded the iOS 7 beta yesterday and, in a tizzy of anticipation, applied it to my phone. Of course at that point I had already heard some of the incredible hyperbole surrounding it: on the one hand, people complaining that it was ugly and unusable, and on the other, that the new flat UI was a stunning successor to the iPhone's increasingly outdated visual design. But I hadn't really heard from many people actually using it -- they were all judging on screenshots and the WWDC keynote videos.</p>

<p>So I wanted to post my impressions and thoughts about the newest iOS update, as someone who's used it for a scant 24 hours. Ultimately I believe Apple still has quite a lot of work to do, but that iOS 7 is a really impressive step in the right direction -- definitely not ready for release immediately, but I'm hopeful that in three months it could be really, truly amazing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Good</h2>

<p>There's a lot to like about iOS 7. Here's my personal favorites.</p>

<h3>UI Transitions</h3>

<p>Apple has invested a lot of time in the easing between screens in iOS 7 and the results are really spectacular. Unlocking your phone, icons flow in seamlessly from the corners of the app.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/162R031R2S0B2r003J0x/unlocking.jpg" alt="Unlocking the Phone" /></p>

<p>And when opening an app or group, you zoom in on it until it takes up the entirety of the screen. All these animations last maybe a quarter of a second, but they look really professional, seamless, and effortless. There's no hitching or stuttering (even on the beta version of the OS), and even the text appears to zoom in smoothly without any jaggies or transformation weirdness.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3q0n0r1e241h2M2S1i1L/zooming.jpg" alt="Zooming to a Group" /></p>

<p>(The jaggies in 1Password above are due to transforming the original image to a more reasonable jpg.)</p>

<p>This effect goes great with the new slightly moving backgrounds, which are serene and peaceful while still giving the slight impression of movement. Overall, the polishing work that went into iOS 7 is immediately obvious, and in motion it really does look extraordinary.</p>

<h3>The Home Screen</h3>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/24062i2D0W2P2R020J0z/home.jpg" alt="New Home Screen" /></p>

<p>The new homepage is gorgeous and simplistic. My husband complained that the grey background of the app groups looks strange, coming from the black background they presently have. They look less like groups now and more like plates, in my opinion, which works but does seem slightly odd.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/2n1j0V1M311a203A3T45/groups.jpg" alt="Group View" /></p>

<p>Similarly, expanded groups are really well done. The slight transparent gray here is way better than the white gray on the home screen. It's great that you can finally put as many items into a group as you want, but unfortunately this can get a little confusing -- now that you don't see little icons of everything in a group, I'm not totally sure what each individual group contains. I've already had to juggle groups around so that I have a better idea of what's inside them, whereas before I could just look at the small summary icons.</p>

<h3>NEWSSTAND CAN GO IN A FOLDER</h3>

<p>Yes, it's true! That one app folder that you always wanted to exile to the darkest corners of your phone (along with Compass and Passbook) can finally be banished forever, and without having to try to trick the iPhone into hiding it for you and then undoing it if you accidentally press on it.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/2i0n1j1O0k3u242N241R/exiled.jpg" alt="Sorry Newsstand" /></p>

<p>And stay dead.</p>

<h3>Spotlight Got Moved</h3>

<p>No longer will swiping all the way left result in the Spotlight screen. Now you search your iPhone by pulling down on the home screen, which shows the spotlight search function above your apps.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/1s3z3d3a1y3F2g0A2c2F/spotlight.jpg" alt="Spotlight" /></p>

<p>This new location is welcome and looks a lot more seamless and natural than an entire empty screen devoted to searching.</p>

<h3>Messages Looks Good for iMessages</h3>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/230T1B1E051e0L0D2o0K/imessage.jpg" alt="iMessage Messages" /></p>

<p>I like the new conversation view for Messages. Some have complained that the gap between two messages is too small and doesn't have enough breathing room -- and they're right that they're probably only three or four pixels separated. But the gap is big enough to see that the messages are distinct without taking up unnecessary real estate, so I don't mind it too much.</p>

<p>There's a neat gradient effect where messages at the top of the app seem more blue than messages at the bottom. Overall this is unobtrusive but still looks professional.</p>

<h3>No Skeumorphism</h3>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0C1h1o131u2z2B3l2h1l/notes.jpg" alt="Notes" /></p>

<p>Finally getting rid of the legal paper look, the new Notes app is as simple as it is useful.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3m1a0y1C2d3x0x2O0Y2N/calendar.jpg" alt="Calendar" /></p>

<p>Similarly Calendar looks clear and great.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0K0N1N152s1V3O2N271z/gamecenter.jpg" alt="Game Center" /></p>

<p>And finally that ratty old green felt is gone, leaving colored bubbles and lovely white clarity.</p>

<p>Overall the removal of the skeumorphisms is an unmixed win for iOS 7, and the new apps are worthy successors to the ugly old ones.</p>

<h3>Multitasking Looks Nifty</h3>

<p>The new multitasking view -- where you see all your open applications and the screen you left open on them -- looks quite nifty.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3y18452t1y1o0T2S0v0X/multitasking.jpg" alt="Multitasking" /></p>

<p>Swiping between open apps is simple and they become immediately responsive when touching them. The carousel of open apps are just images, however: screens don't update while you're looking between them, which makes sense but is a little disappointing.</p>

<h3>Lots More Information</h3>

<p>Because of the flat UI and the smaller lines, Apple seems confident in displaying a lot more information in a smaller space. I think this is good, but it makes me concerned about accessibility. For example, consider the voice mail screen.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0y0b3d2v2F1F2l31090t/voicemail.jpg" alt="Voicemail" /></p>

<p>Now you see all the buttons and sliders that used to be at the bottom of the screen on each individual voicemail. Similarly, when sending a text, instead of a growing bar showing the text's progress you see a line with a height of maybe one or two pixels filling directly underneath the status text:</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0P060r1w3Y28271c1F35/progress.jpg" alt="Messages" /></p>

<p>The density of information means a lot more can be displayed near where you'd expect it to be appear, and in a much more unobtrusive manner.</p>

<h2>The Bad</h2>

<p>These are the things that I hope Apple is still iterating on. None of these issues are really terrible, but they do seem either a little hurried or less polished.</p>

<h3>The New Notifications Pulldown</h3>

<p>The transparency effect looks great: you can sort of see the app underneath notifications, but it's blurry and dimmed. But the "today" view is essentially worthless, and it's the default screen when you pull notifications down.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0P441W0N062k0b3l2e0y/today.jpg" alt="Today Notifications" /></p>

<p>The old notifications view is now under "All", that middle button, that shows you emails and tweets and missed text messages.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/193u3v0R413Z0E3A1K0b/all.jpg" alt="All Notifications" /></p>

<p>You'd think this is what the "Missed" button would do, but nothing displays under that category, leading me to believe it might be broken.</p>

<p>Either way, "All" should definitely be the default view for the notifications screen, since that's what it is in iOS 6. And if you want a worthless computer-generated summary of your day, you should have the option of tapping into that, without it being the first thing you see.</p>

<h3>Messages Looks Bad for Texts</h3>

<p>The gentle gradient that, on iMessages looks so professional, makes text messages vaguely unreadable.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0H2r1z173Z3R1s1V2a0G/texts.jpg" alt="iMessage Texts" /></p>

<p>Note how the green at the top of the text view is almost neon? The gradient for this screen needs to be toned down so that texts are as readable as iMessages. And white on light green might be a bad idea either way.</p>

<h3>The Lock Screen</h3>

<p>The new lock screen is highly mysterious. I've been using an iPhone since they first came out and I initially swiped the wrong direction to unlock iOS 7. Why? I'm not sure, but something about this screen says "swipe right to left" instead of "swipe left to right".</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3B2Q1N3w0X0B1v1d2c1A/lock.jpg" alt="Lock Screen" /></p>

<p>Though I guess I should count myself lucky that it says anything to me at all. The "slide to unlock" text highlights in the proper swiping direction, but too rapidly to really see, so it's easy to imagine a new user coming up to the iPhone and trying to swipe that text every which way before the phone unlocks.</p>

<p>I think it's the lack of the little pull button at the bottom that we've become so frighteningly used to that causes this confusion. This screen gives almost no indication at all which direction you should be swiping: the only arrows present are at the top and bottom, and that's to bring down notifications or bring up the control center. (Both of these can be disabled on the lock screen from preferences, if you so desire.)</p>

<p>Apple should consider adding a swipe button back to this screen so that it's immediately obvious how to unlock the phone.</p>

<h3>The New Toggle Switch</h3>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/1H343k232t09072t0Y3j/toggles.jpg" alt="Toggle Switches" /></p>

<p>This might seem nitpicky, but the new toggle controls are difficult to properly change their state. You can't really drag them anymore: the phone doesn't seem to understand the gesture. If you simply tap a toggle switch it will flip as it should, but who touches a toggle control when you can grab and pull instead?</p>

<h3>You Can't Close Apps Via Multitasking Anymore</h3>

<p>This sort of sucks as a developer, since it was a great way of completely closing an app and then testing its startup on the phone. No longer can you hold down app icons in multitasking and be presented with the option of closing them. Hopefully they add this back in.</p>

<h2>The Ugly</h2>

<p>And finally, there are some parts of iOS 7 so monumentally awful I can only call them "ugly."</p>

<h3>The Receiving Call Screen</h3>

<p>Good lord is this ugly -- like, so bad I wonder if anyone really bothered looking at it before releasing it.</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/2O0L423A1z3l450g1A0X/receiving.jpg" alt="Receiving Call" /></p>

<p>The red on white text is highly unreadable, the buttons are ugly, and the whole thing is just an overly-simplistic mistake. This entire screen needs a significant revamp before it could be called usable, much less pretty.</p>

<h3>Bugs, Bugs, Bugs</h3>

<p>Boy is this a beta version of the OS. I've encountered three different bugs so far:</p>

<ol>
<li>The phone completely bricks if you try to use the system date picker. You have to restore from the original firmware.</li>
<li>Sometimes, all apps will try to update simultaneously and then become stuck updating, meaning you have no working apps at all on the phone. Again, restoring is the only solution.</li>
<li>After multitasking, the background sometimes stays the same size as a multitasking window. The only way to fix it is to restart your phone.</li>
</ol>


<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/241e451X423U1H3G2400/bug.jpg" alt="Bad Background" /></p>

<p>And that's only in 24 hours of using it. To call this unstable is an understatement.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>I'm not a UI designer, and I can't judge the work that Apple has done from a professional standpoint. But speaking as a consumer, I think that iOS 7 represents some great work in improving the iPhone's visual language, heightening the amount of information delivered, and simplifying apps so that this increase of information doesn't seem overwhelming. It also looks stellar in a lot of places... and, unfortunately, pretty darn unpleasant in others.</p>

<p>Certainly Apple has a lot of work to do to make this really visually great. And I can't blame people for being concerned that it looks somewhat similar to the old Metro UI. Still, I think that the final product Apple will deliver to us will have most of these gripes fixed -- in three months' time we'll see an even more visually distinct, even more beautiful final iOS 7. In the meantime, I can't recommend anyone downloads the beta, because while it may look good, it needs a lot of stability improvements before it's truly functional.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
