<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: beginner | Josh Symonds]]></title>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/categories/beginner/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-12T15:15:46-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://joshsymonds.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Symonds]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby in the Sandbox: SandRBox]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/31/ruby-in-the-sandbox-sandrbox/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-31T11:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/31/ruby-in-the-sandbox-sandrbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I volunteer in the cyber center at the <a href="http://www.centeronhalsted.org/">Center on Halsted</a>. They're always looking for people to teach new classes, so I figured I would teach an introduction to programming class -- an introduction through Ruby. Besides being my favorite computer language, I think Ruby makes a great beginner's language: it has none of the strange, computer-oriented concepts that make most programming languages difficult to learn, and it even reads like pure, simple English. Instead of pointers and variable typing, you have sensible enumerators and object orientation. And also it's super fun.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, getting stuff installed on the computers at the cyber center is kind of a headache. Like most chronically underfunded but well-meaning institutions, there are about three levels of bureaucracy between you and getting anything done. And teaching Ruby without the aid of irb would be next to impossible. So what's a guy to do?</p>

<p>Simple: <a href="http://sandrbox.herokuapp.com/">create irb online</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Now, I hear what you're saying: "Josh, that already exists, and it's called <a href="http://tryruby.org/">tryruby.org</a>!" Unfortunately, I don't like tryruby all that much. I have nothing but respect for their mission, but the service itself is achingly slow and frequently it won't work at all. I don't know what they're running it on (the only code I could find on github was months old), but I figured I could whip up something better.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Veraticus/Sandrbox">Turns out I was right</a>. Sandrbox is a simple project that I'm actually pretty proud of; it makes use of some very edge-case metaprogramming concepts to create as secure an irb environment as I could whip up. In addition to removing dangerous methods on classes (and their metaclasses), it has some really nice syntactical sugar that makes it easy to understand where you are in a block. And when the execution of your secure code is done, it restores all the classes and methods that were missing while removing any new ones that were added, guaranteeing that your environment will be exactly the same as before you started executing code.</p>

<p>This is obviously important if you intend to run that code on a server somewhere -- after all, you can't have someone doing something like:</p>

<p><code>ruby
`killall -9 thin` # bad
Kernel.exec("rm -rf /") # worse
</code></p>

<p>These methods when executed in Sandrbox are instead gently sanitized:</p>

<p><code>ruby
Sandrbox.perform(['`killall -9 thin`']).output # =&gt; ["NameError: undefined local variable or method ``' for Kernel:Module"]
Sandrbox.perform(['Kernel.exec("rm -rf /")']).output # =&gt; ["NameError: undefined local variable or method `exec' for Kernel:Module"]
</code></p>

<p>While still allowing you to retain the power and complexity of Ruby:</p>

<p><code>ruby
Sandrbox.perform(['class Foo', 'def test', '"Hi!"', 'end', 'end', 'Foo.new.test']).output # =&gt; [nil, '"Hi!"']
</code></p>

<p>Even cooler is that it automatically does some parsing for you, so that you know when code can be executed or the user is probably not done yet typing:</p>

<p><code>ruby
response = Sandrbox.perform(['class Foo', 'def test'])
response.output # []
response.complete? # false
response.indent_level # 2
response.indent_character # 'def'
</code></p>

<p>I put a small Sinatra app in front of this and made a little site that I also called <a href="http://sandrbox.herokuapp.com/">Sandrbox</a>. I intend to use it in place of irb to teach this introduction to programming course -- it'll make a great tool for putting the power of Ruby in front of people while still being relatively assured that they can't destroy my server (intentionally or accidentally). And the code is really pretty neat, so you should definitely <a href="https://github.com/Veraticus/Sandrbox">check out the repository</a>. I can't say that it's totally secure yet, but it's a damn sight better than uncensored irb, and after a week or two of work I bet I'll be able to get it locked down pretty damn tight.</p>

<p>But until then, go ahead and try to break it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delegation when Delegate Just Won't Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/28/delegation-when-delegate-just-wont-work/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-28T15:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/28/delegation-when-delegate-just-wont-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rails provides a really awesome ability to avoid <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_Demeter">Law of Demeter</a> violations -- the <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/Module/delegate">Module#delegate</a> method. The Law of Demeter is an informal programming guideline, intended to make your code more obvious and more reusable: objects should only call methods on other objects, not objects of those objects. To provide a more concrete example:</p>

<p><code>ruby
  @user.address.street_address # Law of Demeter violation: @user should not reach into address!
  @user.street_address # So much better...
</code></p>

<p>Rails, because it's cool, provides a quick and easy pattern for making this work:</p>

<p>```ruby
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_one :address
  delegate :street_address, :to => :address</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>User.new.street_address # Calls address.street_address
```</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/Module/delegate">delegate documentation</a> for more information on how this functionality works. But <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9914400/delegate-all-method-calls-on-a-model-to-an-association">a question I came across on Stack Overflow</a> today asked: what do you when you want to delegate all methods? I do <a href="https://github.com/Veraticus/Dynamoid/blob/master/lib/dynamoid/adapter.rb#L122">something similar in Dynamoid</a> and wanted to talk about how to make this pattern sensible and performant.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Essentially you have two options when delegation fails: the easy but less performant way, and the hard but more performant way. It's always nice to have choices, right?</p>

<h2>The Easy Way</h2>

<p>The easy way uses <code>method_missing</code>. Method_missing, of course, is part of Ruby's extensive metaprogramming suite; it is called when a method that doesn't exist is invoked on an object. So, if you have an object (say our user from above) and you want to delegate all methods that it doesn't have itself to its address, you would simply do:</p>

<p>```ruby
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_one :address</p>

<p>  def method_missing(method, *args)</p>

<pre><code>return address.send(method, *args) if address &amp;&amp; address.respond_to?(method)
super
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>This works and will correctly send every method that can be called on an address to that address. Unfortunately, method_missing is slower than defining a method directly on the object, so every time you're forced to use method_missing you're added fractions of milliseconds to your application. This speed difference is usually imperceptible, but you never know: if you use this method_missing enough it could make a difference.</p>

<h2>The Hard Way</h2>

<p>So we have the hard way. This method is "harder" only in that you need to know the methods you want to delegate beforehand -- in which case, why aren't you using <code>delegate</code>? There is still a use for this method though: if you want to do something like benchmarking or argument recording before you delegate, you can do that easily here.</p>

<p>```ruby
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_one :address</p>

<p>  [:all, :my, :methods, :here].each do |m|</p>

<pre><code>define_method(m) do |*args|
  address.send(m, *args)
end 
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  end
```</p>

<p>In Dynamoid, we perform benchmarking in this method before sending the response along, allowing you to see how long the actual request took in DynamoDB.</p>

<p>Ultimately, you should use <code>delegate</code> if possible... but if it isn't, then either of these two options should get you started to avoid programming unpleasantness. Don't address your objects through other objects -- your code will look better and be more maintainable if you take some time to isolate methods!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Classifying and Refactoring Your Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/16/classifying-and-refactoring-your-code/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-16T00:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/16/classifying-and-refactoring-your-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Outside of the guiding framework of Rails, it can be difficult to manage your own Ruby code, as I've discovered in the process of creating <a href="https://github.com/Veraticus/Dynamoid">Dynamoid</a>. MVC provides a clear and concise framework that encapsulates the functionality of most web applications really well; but outside of web applications, exactly where and how to put your code is a lot less clear. I thought I'd share some of my experiences and thoughts on doing this in my own Gem in the hopes that the lessons I've learned will aid others.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Hashes = Objects</h2>

<p>In the earlier iterations of Dynamoid, I was passing around almost everything in hashes, and the calculations I was performing on those hashes was growing more and more complicated as I went, with logic flying around my files like a flock of disorganized birds. When I was putting index logic into criteria chains, I realized that keeping indexes as hashes was an enormous mistake... and one I wish I had realized earlier.</p>

<p>As I was refactoring my code I realized that I pass hashes around in a number of places. Hashes work well initially to store small amounts of data, but if you're using them for that purpose you almost certainly want a real object instead. Just whip that hash apart into a class and you'll be surprised how much code will go in there, and how much simpler your application will be for your trouble.</p>

<h2>Refactor Early, Refactor Often</h2>

<p>I tend to be my own harshest critic, but honestly, my first pass at features tends to be messy at best. I make my tests pass (always test first, btw, but that's so fundamental I'm not going to include it as a point) but usually in the most complicated, slowest, unpleasant way possible. Take some time after the tests pass to stare at your code a bit and decide if that's really the best way to go about doing things. Usually a change will jump out at you immediately, but don't be afraid to just come back to the code later if nothing presents itself.</p>

<p>Tests allow you to do this kind of refactoring free of charge. I always imagine tests as the scaffolding around my code; no matter how tall the code gets, with the scaffolding it'll never fall over.</p>

<h2>Document!</h2>

<p>I'm really bad at this one myself, but I'm going to be going back through Dynamoid in the very near future and adding documentation to all my methods. Even if your code is a one-liner, people will read documentation over code every time. So document that code! Especially in a collaborative environment, documentation is critical for making your project easy to contribute to.</p>

<p>I'm sure other things will pop out at me after some thought, but these are the biggest takeaways Dynamoid has given me. Hopefully they'll be of use to someone else as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Mess With Primary Keys]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/04/dont-mess-with-primary-keys/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-04T19:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/03/04/dont-mess-with-primary-keys</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/1224374/veraticus">I really like answering questions on Stack Overflow</a> -- it's like a trivia game that you win by knowing Rails backwards and forwards, but instead of cheesy prizes you get awesome reputation points! And also little badges!</p>

<p>Recently I've been seeing a lot of beginner-style questions, and the most popular has definitely been some variant of "how do I mess with the primary key column?"</p>

<p>The answer is always, invariably, the same: don't.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It might seem sensible to tuck some sort of business logic away into your primary key. Just earlier today, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9558715/changing-models-id-type-from-integer-to-decimal-makes-all-entries-try-to-be-0-0/9558832#9558832">I answered a question</a> from a guy who wanted to turn his primary key column into a decimal, and have the part before the decimal be equal to the primary key of another table -- so you'd have 75.001 and 75.002, with 75 being the primary key of the orders table. A cute idea for a new column like order_number or something like that, but just a plain awful idea for a primary key.</p>

<p>Primary keys, when you get right down to it, are database artifacts. They're useful because they allow databases to expose powerful relations for our data: without a way for databases to reference individual rows that are guaranteed to be unique, even the most basic joins would be impossible. And because they're important for databases, the assumption seems to be that they're important for people too.</p>

<p>Part of this is Rails' fault. By exposing URLs with primary keys by default (like users/4), one would automatically assume that the primary key is important data for a user to know (your key is 4 and that's important!). In reality nothing could be further from the truth: the ID for a user is arbitrary database-internal logic and has no business facing users at all. I wish Rails going forward came bundled with the really awesome <a href="https://github.com/norman/friendly_id">FriendlyId</a> Gem that makes some unique database column appear to your internal application logic as the real ID for that table. Then you'd have URLs like users/josh, and that both looks better and obfuscates the primary key.</p>

<p>As a sidenote, this is why UUID-based keys like <a href="http://www.mongodb.org/display/DOCS/Object+IDs">MongoDB's</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Veraticus/Dynamoid">Dynamoid's</a> are rather nifty -- they make really ugly ID-based URLs by default so force you to choose a better column to use as a URL slug.</p>

<p>The problem with all this attention on the primary key is that, invariably, people want to change it. Changing primary keys is awful. It will disassociate data all throughout your database, it messes with table autoincrementing... it will lead to problems right at the moment, and even more down the road you won't even foresee. Or even worse, you'll want to choose something nonstandard as a primary key (or not choose one at all) -- and you'll want to perform a join and be forced to deal with the consequences of your decision. Hint: they won't be pretty.</p>

<p>So do yourself a favor. View the ID column as what it really is: an internal database construction. It should be an auto-incrementing integer, no excuses. If you want any kind of business logic, make a new column for it and manage it separately. You'll be glad you did, I promise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
