<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business | Hi, I'm Josh Symonds]]></title>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-27T20:10:25-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://joshsymonds.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Symonds]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking Up With GirlsGuideTo]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/12/27/breaking-up-with-girlsguideto/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-27T19:40:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/12/27/breaking-up-with-girlsguideto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's never easy to decide to move on, particularly when you're a cofounder. It definitely feels less like a business shakeup and more like a real breakup.</p>

<p>But I must announce that my time at GirlsGuideTo has officially ended.</p>

<p>I'm proud of the work I've done for GirlsGuideTo. I took a <a href="http://old.girlsguideto.com/home">decrepit, slow PHP Drupal installation</a> and turned it into a <a href="http://girlsguideto.com/">speedy, modernized Rails application</a>. The new GirlsGuideTo uses some incredibly modern technologies to be fast, while still being maintainable and consistent. The pages load near-instantly thanks to <a href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/12/18/making-your-web-pages-ridiculously-fast-without-breaking-them/">head.js and Turbolinks</a>, and the Rails code is well-separated and highly tested thanks to some awesome concerns and really nifty Rack middleware.</p>

<p>It also features a really kickass design from my friend <a href="https://twitter.com/LukesBeard">@LukesBeard</a>, so it also looks great in addition to feeling great.</p>

<p>Though I'm moving to greener pastures, I'm sure GirlsGuideTo has a bright future ahead of them. As for me, I'm doing some work for <a href="http://everest.com/">Everest</a> -- they're really awesome people that need their backend scaled right into infinity, and I think I'm the guy to do it for them. In fact, if you download the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/everest-live-your-dreams-achieve/id581016826?mt=8">super cool free app</a> or have downloaded it at launch, you've already touched some of my code! The best part about onboarding quickly is having code live in production almost immediately.</p>

<p>So keep on watching this spot for more of the same that you've come to expect -- adrenaline-filled posts on the exciting world of server scalability and optimization.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Not to Apply for a Job]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/06/20/how-not-to-apply-for-a-job/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-20T22:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/06/20/how-not-to-apply-for-a-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been looking about two weeks now for a really fantastic designer for GirlsGuideTo -- a designer that's as fabulous as the site itself. Somewhat surprisingly, given how many people are unemployed or underemployed, my search has been really difficult. And not because of a dearth of responses: in fact, quite the opposite. I estimate I've received more than a hundred resumes in response to Craigslist postings, LinkedIn listings, and advertising in Dribbbble. And most surprising to me is the fact that the vast majority of these responses just aren't very good.</p>

<p>I'm sure that many of these resumes and coverletters come from experienced, seasoned professionals with a genuine and burning desire to be paid -- a desire that is equally matched by my hunger to pay them for the amazing work they can do. But frankly, you wouldn't know it from reading their letters. 99.9% of them are just... <em>bad</em>. So, I've taken the time to distill the mountain of resumes in my inbox into three succinct lessons. If you're going to apply for a job, please take them to heart before writing your potential employer. Not only will you increase the chances you'll actually be hired, but they will definitely thank you for breaking the tide of mediocrity that is surely washing over them. If you're the one to stand out, believe me... you'll get noticed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Don't Copy and Paste</h2>

<p>Easily the most common mistake I see -- the one that is most likely to make me entirely skip a candidate -- is that the cover letter is copied and pasted. It either doesn't include my company name (GirlsGuideTo is somewhat distinctive), or even more embarrassing, is addressed to a different company's name. I can always tell when I'm reading a copy/pasted letter. It's generic and boring; it enumerates talents and skills that I have no need for and didn't include in my job listing.</p>

<p>I took the time to hand-craft the job posting you read. I know you're probably applying to lots of jobs, and I sympathize that being without work -- or trying to find a new job -- is arduous and unpleasant. But if you want to be seriously considered, you must include three things in your cover letter:</p>

<ol>
<li>The name of the company you're applying to,</li>
<li>The position in the company you're applying for,</li>
<li>Why your skills make you a perfect fit for that position.</li>
</ol>


<p>The third one is obviously the most complicated but also the most necessary. The degree to which you customize your cover letter for the target job will be directly proportional to the number of people that respond positively to it. Believe me, I can tell which people actually wrote even a few choice words actually responding to my listing.</p>

<p>They are the ones that I will write back.</p>

<h2>Don't Make Me Find You</h2>

<p>If you're an Internet professional -- web designer, programmer, usability expert, whatever -- you must have an online presence. It can be as simple as your LinkedIn profile, but ideally should be a portfolio, with your own personalized URL, summarizing the work you've done, hopefully with lots of links and (even better) pictures. You should link to this summary of you in your cover letter. Be proud of it; include it in the first or second sentence. Say something like, "You can find my resume, and my portfolio, online at http://myattractivenamehere.com. But the parts that are most directly pertinent to you are..." And then go on to list the jobs that you've done that make you perfect for me!</p>

<p>Don't include a list of twenty links in your coverletter, saying they're you're work. If I'm feeling gracious I might click on the first two. Chances are they won't be what I'm looking for, and then I'll consign your resume to the dustbin of defeat. (This outcome might have been averted if you had twenty thumbnails I could quickly glance over on your portfolio, though.)</p>

<p>And for Heaven's sake include some kind of link to yourself! Anything at all works. If you're really an Internet professional and not just some high school student -- or even if you ARE a high school student -- you should have an online presence somewhere. If you don't include links in your resume or your cover letter, the chances of me Googling you to find them are absolutely zero. As are the chances of you landing this job.</p>

<h2>Don't Make Me Read Your Resume</h2>

<p>This is a harsh truth, but one I've heard again and again from people who have to make hiring decisions:</p>

<p>We don't read resumes unless we've already decided we're interested in a candidate.</p>

<p>Your cover letter is going to be your one and only chance to sell yourself. Go all out. If you have skills that you feel are directly applicable to the position, mention them in the cover letter, and then explain why those skills make you suited for the work. Your previous experiences that give you unique and valuable insight into the job should be front and center, in the letter itself.</p>

<p>And most likely, the second place I go, after reading your cover letter, won't be your resume either. It'll be your online presence, either your portfolio or sample sites you've linked me to. I'll only open your resume after I've already decided you're most likely a good fit -- and to be honest, I probably won't read it very closely anyway, since by that point I've already made a decision.</p>

<p>I know this seems unfair. You might be perfect for me; your resume even lists your numerous and varied accomplishments that make you my ideal match. But your competitor, with a very similar set of experiences, actually told me her accomplishments in her first paragraph. She drew my attention right to them -- I didn't even have to look in her resume to start being impressed by her. When I open her portfolio, I'll see that she's right. She <em>is</em> perfect for me. And then she goes on the shortlist, and you and your perfect resume are skipped over, unopened.</p>

<p>What I'm really trying to say with this small list of "don'ts" is very simply this: don't get lost in the crowd. I don't care if the designer we end up choosing is a guy or girl, Chicagoan or San Franciscoan, experienced or freshly graduated. (Also it's illegal for me to care, but that's beside the point.) All that really matters to me is that they're good; and more than being good, they're not afraid to say, "I'm perfect for you, and here's why."</p>

<p>And, honestly, that's all that matters to any prospective employer from their applicants. If you really want to be hired, then you'll have to show that you respect the time and energy they've invested in conducting a search for someone like you. Write plainly and to impress -- cram your cover letter with customized material, responding directly to the job posting. Include links early and often to your online presence. And fill your letter with proof after repeated proof that you are the ideal match they've been searching for.</p>

<p>Do all that, and you'll get a response to each and every one of your applications. And, hopefully, most of those responses will be positive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving On]]></title>
    <link href="http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/05/31/moving-on/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-31T16:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joshsymonds.com/blog/2012/05/31/moving-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I try to keep to a schedule of a post every three days, and I've definitely not been keeping on top of that -- I haven't posted for almost a week and a half now. I apologize for the lack of content; in my defense, I've been deep in negotiations that have resulted in some exciting personal changes. Changes that should hopefully make this modest blog even more interesting!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Leaving Hipstamatic</h2>

<p>I'm leaving my position as web director of Synthetic. I love the company and the product -- I think Hipstamatic has a bright future ahead of it, and it is, in my opinion, easily the best photography app on the market. But my professional growth there had stalled. I was having lots of fun juggling servers, code, customer service, database administration, and, well, everything else technical. Yet I was hungry for more: specifically, opportunities to execute and pursue my own technical vision as a valued partner, not just a valued employee. I wanted to be a decision maker.</p>

<p>Synthetic has always been a company driven by design. You can see it in any of their <a href="http://makebeautiful.hipstamatic.com/">amazing</a> <a href="http://gear.hipstamatic.com">sites</a> (featuring stellar HTML, CSS, and JS by the incomparable <a href="http://lukesbeard.com/">@LukesBeard</a>), and even the design of the Hipstamatic itself, which is retro and cool and usable all at once. But for an ambitious technical guy, direction through design didn't leave a lot of opportunity for personal growth. I knew if I wanted to let my voice be heard, I'd have to go somewhere else to do it.</p>

<h2>Joining GirlsGuideTo</h2>

<p>So what's next for Josh Symonds?</p>

<p>I accepted an offer from <a href="http://girlsguideto.com">GirlsGuideTo</a>, an insanely fabulous website for women, to be their CTO and co-founder. Having recently secured a round of seed financing, GirlsGuideTo is positioned really excellently. They have a huge userbase and are poised to really take over their market; their only stumbling block is some really old software and a somewhat dated design. Those are problems I can fix! Within the next month, I intend to give the site a complete graphical and technical overhaul. Under my technical direction (and CEO Brette Borow's product management), GirlsGuideTo will grow to be an even more amazing site -- the premiere destination for women to get advice, read awesome articles, and connect with one another.</p>

<p>Within the next couple weeks, I also intend to release my first RubyMotion application to the iTunes App Store. Featuring some excellent designs by the aforementioned <a href="http://lukesbeard.com/">@LukesBeard</a> and some pretty nifty code by yours truly, it represents the culmination of nearly a month spent working during almost all my free time. I think it's pretty cool, and I'll be spending some time discussing its technical infrastructure and how I used RubyMotion to make it happen.</p>

<p>Finally, what does all this mean for my blog? Well, I'll still post awesome code and go on and on about how much I love Ruby. But I'll also be talking about the trials and tribulations of a newly-minted CTO at a new startup; finding talent, putting it to use, and in general conquering the world one step at a time. And I promise to get back on my regular, three-day schedule while I do it.</p>

<p>So stick around and keep reading; this blog will only get more interesting!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
